Inventory of the Henry M. Wriston Collection, 1916 - 1972
Henry M. Wriston Collection, 1916 - 1972
- Speeches
  - Character in Action. Convocation, Brown. September 24, 1941. Brown Alumni Monthly. October 1941
  - After the War, What? Controllers Institute of America, New York. September 30, 1941
  - United We Give. United Campaign Dinner, Pawtucket. October 20, 1941
  - Government of Laws. October 23, 1941
  - "Laws and Men." Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. October 28, 1941
  - Government Use of the Machine in War. American Academy of Political Science Dinner, New York. November 13, 1941
  - As a Little Child. Convocation- Wesleyan University. November 23, 1941
  - Youth, Farm and Home. December 3, 1941
  - Wake Up, America. Broadcast Debate with T.V. Smith, New York American Economic Foundation. December 7, 1941
  - Statement on War. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. December 9, 1941
  - Unity For War and For Peace. Bond Club, New York. December 17, 1941
  - Long View on Strategy. American Political Science Association, New York. December 3, 1941
  - Abraham Lincoln. Temple Bethel Brotherhood, Providence. February 12, 1942
  - Levee-En-Masse. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. March 3, 1942
  - Sub-Soil of Peace. Phi Beta Kappa Dinner, Providence. Library Quarterly v. 12:3. March 7, 1942
  - Mote-Pluckers or Beam-Casters. Under the Elms, Brown. May 15, 1942
  - Never Underestimate the Power of a Woman. Ivy Day, Pembroke. May 15, 1942
  - Leadership. Pembroke Semi-Centennial Convocation. May 16, 1942
  - World Charter. Annual Alumni Meeting, Sayles Hall. May 18, 1942
  - Normalcy. Convocation- Sayles Hall. June 22, 1942
  - Losing the War. Pembroke Assembly, Providence. August 4, 1942
  - Recruiting College Students. Special Meeting, Sayles Hall, Brown. September 11, 1942
  - Getting Ready to Go to War. Commencement First Baptist Meeting House, Providence. October 5, 1942
  - Reading About the War. Friends of the Library, Providence. October 5, 1942
  - Do it Now. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. October 13, 1942
  - United War Fund and Lease-Lend. Speakers Bureau, Providence. October 13, 1942
  - Alumni Dinner- Security, Homecoming, Providence. October 17, 1942
  - Wartime Program-Nationally. Wisconsin Citizens Public Expenditure Survey, Milwaukee. October 27, 1942
  - Substitute of Unity. United War Fund, Biltmore, Providence. October 30, 1942
  - War Production Conference Welcome. Providence. November 12, 1942
  - In Union There is Strength. United War Fund Rally, Providence. November 12, 1942
  - Liberal Education and the War. Pembroke Assembly. December 1, 1942
  - Sons of God. Convocation, Wesleyan University. November 15, 1942
  - Problem of the Liberal Arts College. American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Boston. January 13, 1943
  - Does Liberty Consist in Two Dollars a Day Extra? Class Day, Brown. February 2, 1943
  - What Can I Do For the War Effort. Class Day, Pembroke. February 1, 1943
  - Social Hypochondria. Alumni Advisory Council, Providence. February 20, 1943
  - New and Old Bill of Rights Compared. New England Council, Providence. March 12, 1943
  - Future of the Liberal Arts. Brown Club, Boston. March 31, 1943
  - Army Indoctrination Lectures. 6 Lectures. April-May 1943
  - Calm and Crisis. Chapel- All Classes. May 4, 1943
  - Recruiting Students for Pembroke. Alumnae Meeting. May 29, 1943
  - Reality of a Liberal Education. Class Day, Brown. June 1, 1943
  - How to Achieve the Inevitable. Commencement, Brown. June 2, 1943
  - Sensitivity. Convocation, Alumnae Hall, Brown. July 6, 1943
  - Coherence. Assembly, Pembroke. July 13, 1944
  - First Steps in Peace Making. American Bankers Association, New York. September 15, 1943
  - Graduation- Pre-Meteorological Army Unit. World Organization or Alliance. September 17, 1943
  - Which Freedom for China? Chapel, Brown. September 28, 1943
  - Endowed Freedom. Inauguration of Victor Lloyd Butterfield as President of Wesleyan University. October 23, 1943
  - Post-War Education. New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Boston. December 3, 1943
  - Free Enterprise. National Association of Manufacturers, New York. December 10, 1943
  - Coming Crises. Navy Unit, Brown. December 17, 1943
  - Remarks to John Carter Brown. Library Associates. January 10, 1944
  - Significance of Christian Principals. Brown Christian Association. January 20, 1944
  - Functional Approach to Peace. New York Chamber of Commerce, New York. March 2, 1944
  - Victory F.O.B. Radio Broadcast WPRO (Columbia Network). March 18, 1944
  - Education in the Post-War World. Brown Club, New York. March 23, 1944
  - What is Man? Commencement, University of Vermont. May 29, 1944
  - Selling America Short. Navy Unit, Brown. June 2, 1944
  - What of the Returning Soldier. Commencement Alumni Meeting. June 19, 1944
  - Use of Force for Peace. Chapel, Brown. September 19, 1944
  - Treaty of Peace. Brown Christian Association, Faunce House. October 5, 1944
  - Future of Germany. Assembly, Pembroke. September 28, 1944
  - Morality as a Function of Politics. Baccalaureate, Brown. October 22, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Dewey v. Roosevelt. Student Political Action Committee, Faunce House. November 6, 1944
  - To the Memory of Andrew Carnegie. Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, Dinner New York. November 15, 1944
  - Political Aspects of the War in 1945. Chapel, Brown. January 2, 1945
  - Effective Democracy. Chamber of Commerce, Providence. January 15, 1945
  - Opportunity or Privelege. February 25, 1945
  - Industrial Research and the Mechanics Program. Industrial Research Directors, New York. March 16, 1945
  - Responsibility of the Individual. Pembroke Assembly. April 3, 1945
  - Remarks at V-E Day Convocation. May 8, 1945
  - Educational Housing. Alumni Meeting, Sayles. June 18, 1945
  - Private Life of the Mind. Chapel, Brown. September 18, 1945
  - Babel. Chapel, Brown. November 13, 1945
  - Deservedly Confident. Chapel, Brown. January 22, 1946
  - Provision for Tomorrow. Alumni Advisory Council. March 16, 1946
  - Vitality. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. March 19, 1946
  - Yesterday and Today. Saint George's School, Middletown, Rhode Island. May 25, 1946
  - The Sphinx Speaks. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. June 4, 1946
  - Veterans' Extension Division Welcome, Brown. September 25, 1946
  - Doing and Reading. Convocation, Brown. September 25, 1946
  - Independent Mind. Convocation, Pembroke. September 26, 1946
  - Quest for Peace. Inauguration of James Case, Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, Pennsylvania. October 25, 1946
  - The Next Step. Educational Records Bureau, New York. October 31, 1946
  - Economic Democracy. Chamber of Commerce, Pawtucket. December 2, 1946
  - Brown and the Community. Campaign Dinner, Providence. December 3, 1946
  - Precise Fears and Vague Hopes. Junior-Senior Convocation. January 9, 1947
  - University, A Beautiful Place. February 18, 1947
  - Lilienthal. Freshman-Sophomore Convocation. February 19, 1947
  - America's Leadership Toward World Government. Student Federalists, Brown. February 26, 1947
  - Crossley as I know Him. American Institute of Chemists, New York. May 2, 1947
  - Gideon's Mastery. Freshman-Sophomore Chapel. May 21, 1947
  - Alienation of the Intellectuals. Alumni Dinner, Brown. June 15, 1947
  - Deal Courageously. East Dennis Church, Massachusetts. August 10, 1947
  - Freshman Dinner, Sayles Hall, Brown. September 15, 1947
  - Crisis-1947 Style. Convocation, Brown. September 24, 1947
  - Science and the Liberal Arts. Carnegie Foundation, New York. November 19, 1947
  - Should there be an Ivy League? Varsity B Club, Sayles Hall. November 25, 1947
  - Local Irresponsibility. Rotary Club Luncheon for Francis J. Brady. December 2, 1947
  - Where Do We Go From Here? New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Boston. December 12, 1947
  - Discontent. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. January 2, 1948
  - Precise Fears and Vague Hopes. Stevens Institute of Technology. January 31, 1948
  - Remarks to Brown Club. February 18, 1948
  - The Marshall Plan. Rally, Sayles Hall. March 5, 1948
  - Science and the Scientist. Sigma Xi Dinner, Providence. April 15, 1948
  - Not as Other Men. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. April 2, 1948
  - National Defense. Coffee House, Faunce House, Brown. April 22, 1948
  - Graduate Education. New England Conference on Graduate Education, Brown. April 30, 1948
  - Observations on Foreign Language Teaching. New England Modern Language Association, Brown. May 8, 1948
  - Charles Evans Hughes. Convocation, Brown. September 29, 1948
  - Perspective. Convocation, Pembroke. September 30, 1948
  - Private Collges. Alumni, Vermont (Rutland). October 6, 1948
  - A Fire Bell in the Night. October 13, 1948
  - The Beam and the Mote. Freshman Chapel, Brown. November 16, 1948
  - The President's Commission. American Association of University Women, Providence. November 9, 1948
  - Implications of the Report of the President's Commission on Higher Education. New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Boston. December 3, 1948
  - Security (III). Sophomore Chapel, Brown. December 8, 1948
  - Peace (II). Junior Chapel, Brown. December 9, 1948
  - Political Strategy for Business. January 19, 1949
  - Federal Aid to Education. Rhode Island Secondary Principals Association, Brown. January 26, 1949
  - Relations of politics and University. Assembly, Wesleyan University. March 3, 1949
  - Dare We Choose Peace. March 7, 1949
  - Not by Bread Alone. March 10, 1949
  - Choosing a Concentration. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. April 20, 1949
  - Un-American Textbooks. Alumni Dinner, Brown. June 17, 1949
  - Remarks. Brown Club, Hartford. September 8, 1949
  - Who Besides the Russians? New England Council, York Harbor, Maine. September 16, 1949
  - Escape From Naivite. September 29, 1949
  - Conservation. New England Tax Officials Assn., Providence. October 6, 1949
  - Yugoslav Relief. United Yugolsav Relief Fund Dinner, New York. October 18, 1949
  - Vocation and Liberal Education. Placement Talks, Brown. November 3, 1949
  - College Graduate and Research. Associated Industries of Rhode Island, and National Association of Manufacturers, Providence. November 4, 1949
  - Imperialists. Freshman Convocation, Brown. November 22, 1949
  - Bread or Freedom. December 17, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Which Way Independence? January 7, 1950
  - A Clinical Report. January 24, 1950
  - State Department and Peace. March 9, 1950
  - Policy v. Action. Lincoln Society Coffee Hour, Brown. April 17, 1950
  - Preacher as Teacher. Yale University Divinity School. April 18, 1950
  - The President and the College. Coffee Hour, Faunce House. May 8, 1950
  - Economic Life XVI: Teaching. Rainbow. May 1950
  - The Meeting House and the University. Northern Baptist Convention, First Baptist Meeting House, Providence. May 22, 1950
  - Education for Democracy. Providence College Commencement. June 6, 1950
  - College Teachers in the Free Society. Harvard Foundation for Advanced Study and Research, Dinner, Cambridge. June 20, 1950
  - Your Reasonable Service. Convocation, Brown. September 18, 1950
  - A Modern Myth. Colgate Founder's Day, Hamilton, New York. September 21, 1950
  - Outlook for the Independent College. Middlebury College Sesquicentennial, Middlebury, Vermont. September 29, 1950
  - Political Strategy for Business. Economic Club, Chicago. April 26, 1949
  - Education of a Minister for Today's World. Colgate-Rochester Divinity School, Laymen's Dinner, Rochester, New York.
  - What Next in Korea? Sophomore Chapel, Brown. October 18, 1950
  - Faith (II). Religious Embassy Group, Brown. November 6, 1950
  - Financial Prospects of American Colleges. TIAA Annual Dinner, New York. November 16, 1950
  - Preventing War. Senior Chapel, Brown. December 1, 1950
  - Admission Officer and Registrar From the President's Point of View. New England Association of Collegiate Registrars, Providence. December 2, 1950
  - Tensions. Convocation, Pembroke. February 1, 1951
  - Washington and Citizenship. Sophomore-Junior Chapel, Brown. February 22, 1951
  - Alumni Speech. Brown Club, New York. April 12, 1951
  - MacArthur's Recall. Freshman Chapel, Brown. April 18, 1951
  - Anglo-American Relations. Coffee Hour, Faunce House. April 19, 1951
  - MacArthur's Speech. Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. April 20, 1951
  - British-American Tensions. Faculty Club Luncheon. May 2, 1951
  - Kefauver Report. Sophomore-Junior Chapel, Brown. May 3, 1951
  - Freedom (II). Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. May 11, 1951
  - How to Live Together and Like It. National Board of Fire Underwriters, New York. May 24, 1951
  - One Hundred Years- Success or Failure. Hill School, Pottstown, Pennsylvania. June 9, 1951
  - Valioity of Limited Objectives. Naval College, Newport. September 10, 1951
  - What is it All About: The Idea of a University. Convocation, Brown. September 17, 1951
  - Avoid Materialistic Objectives. James Bowdoin Exercises. October 17, 1951
  - Obsolescence. Freshman Chapel, Brown. December 5, 1951
  - Foreign Policy and College Students. Sophomore-Junior Chapel. December 6, 1951
  - Straight Line-Shortest Distance. American Mathematical Society, Providence. December 28, 1951
  - New Order. Phi Beta Kappa, Brown. February 20, 1952
  - Role of Higher Education in Furthering the Security of the Nation. West Point Sesquicentennial. March 5, 1952
  - American Leadership. Chancellor's Dinner, Syracuse University. April 26, 1952
  - Fifteenth Brown Network Celebration. Broadcast WEAN. April 30, 1952
  - Basic Factors Influencing our Strategy. Naval War College, Newport. June 11, 1952
  - Sword of Damooles. Convocation, Brown. September 15, 1952
  - Freedom for Eastern Europe. Freshman Chapel, Brown. September 24, 1952
  - Unification of Europe. Sophomore-Junior Chapel. September 25, 1952
  - Nixon and Stevenson Funds. Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. September 26, 1952
  - Politics-1952. Student Rally, Sayles Hall, Brown. October 9, 1952
  - Inauguration of James Stacy Coles, Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine. October 13, 1952
  - Cox Committee Hearing on Foundation. Washington D.C., November 21, 1952
  - Fraternities. National Interfraternity Conference Award. November 28, 1952
  - Great Britain. Barus Lecture, Alumnae Hall. December 10, 1952
  - Prejudice. Freshman Chapel, Brown. January 7, 1953
  - Academic Freedom (II). Alumni Advisor Council, Providence. January 31, 1953
  - Academic Freedom (III). Phi Beta Kappa, Providence. March 5, 1953
  - Academic Freedom. American Association of University Professors. March 31, 1953
  - French-American Relationships. Alliance Francaise, Providence. April 11, 1953
  - Who Should Go to College. Rhode Island School Superintendents Association, Providence. April 15, 1953
  - Freedom from Fear. Freshman Chapel, Brown. April 15, 1953
  - Education on the Razor's Edge. Southern Methodist University, Dallas. May 12, 1953
  - Southampton Toast. Installation of Chancellor, University Dinner, Southampton, England. July 3, 1953
  - If Wishes Were Horses. Convocation, Brown. September 21, 1953
  - Spiritual Hospitality. Vesper Service, Brown. September 27, 1953
  - Character and Vocation. Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. October 14, 1953
  - Corporate Gifts. New England Colleges Fund Luncheon, Boston. October 20, 1953
  - Ideology of the West. Naval War College, Newport. October 23, 1953
  - Voices of America. Leaders of Institutes on World Affairs, New York. October 27, 1953
  - Dare to be a Daniel. Senior Chapel, Brown. December 2, 1953
  - Greetings to President Pusey. Harvard Club, Boston. December 7, 1953
  - How to Live with Allies. Institute of Life Insurance, New York. December 10, 1953
  - Freedom (III). Sophomore Chapel, Brown. January 7, 1954
  - Fraternities and Discrimination. Open Meeting, Brown. February 22, 1954
  - Future of the College President. Founders Day, Union College, Schenectady, New York. February 25, 1954
  - The Cold Peace. Phi Beta Kappa, Brown. March 4, 1954 (Box 7)
  - The Spirit Giveth Life. Freshman Chapel, Brown. April 2, 1954
  - Foreign Service (II). Overseas Writers, Washington. April 22, 1954
  - Foreign Service (III). Faculty Club Luncheon, Brown. May 10, 1954
  - Foreign Service IV. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. May 13, 1954
  - Let us Have Peace. Centennial Convocation, Rhode Island College of Education, Providence. May 16, 1954
  - Policies for Higher Education. Fourth Bicentennial Conference, Columbia University, New York. June 3, 1954
  - McCarthy and Senate Reform. Under the Elms, Brown. June 4, 1954
  - Jewish Tercentenary. State House, Providence., 1954
  - Stars in Their Courses. Convocation, Pembroke. September 1954
  - Freedom or Tyranny. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. October 7, 1954
  - Is There an American Creed. Conference, Wellesley College. October 13, 1954
  - Pride Goeth Before a Fall. Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. October 20, 1954
  - Be Yourself. Freshman Chapel, Brown. October 23, 1954
  - At Red Feather Luncheon. Community Chest Campaign, Providence. November 5, 1954
  - Peace (III). Vespers, Brown. November 21, 1954
  - Freedom (II). Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. December 1, 1954
  - Paine's (Common Sense). Radio Invitation to Learning, CBS. December 12, 1954
  - Reflection Time. Junior-Senior Chapel. December 15, 1954
  - India and the United States and the Impact on South East Asia and the Far East. Rhode Island Teachers in-Service, Providence. January 4, 1955
  - International Development: 1954 in Review. Oberlin College Assembly. January 6, 1955
  - Academic Deans. American Conference of Academic Deans. January 11, 1955
  - Truth in All its Forms. Founders Day, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia. January 15, 1955
  - Remarks to Alumni Advisory Council, Providence. February 5, 1955
  - Liberal Arts at Mid-Century. Men's Club, Hitchcock Church, Scarsdale, New York. February 25, 1955
  - Foreign Service (II). Career Planning Committee, Brown. March 7, 1955
  - United States: Paradox or Power. Association of International Relations Clubs, St. Louis. April 1, 1955
  - Educational Facilities and Prospects in Providence in Higher Education. Radio, WHIM broadcast. April 12, 1955
  - Evening on College Hill. Television Interview, WJAR. May 3, 1955
  - Babel (II). Junior-Senior Chapel, Brown. April 13, 1955
  - Choosing a New College President. Faculty Club Luncheon, Brown. May 4, 1955
  - Banding Conference. Sophomore Chapel, Brown. May 5, 1955
  - Perspective on Security. Conference on Overseas Information Service. May 6, 1955
  - V-E Day- Ten Years Later. May 11, 1955
  - How to Finance Higher Education in the Future. Conference on Financing Higher Education, University of Pennsylvania. May 21, 1955
  - United States as a World Power. American Iron and Steel Institute, New York. May 26, 1955
  - Political Factors in National Strategy. Global Strategy Group, Naval War College, Newport. June 8, 1955
  - Looking at the College Presidency in Retrospect. Institute of College and University Administration, Harvard. June 24, 1955
  - The Foreign Service and Representation Abroad. American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia. November 10, 1955
  - Wriston Recorded: Wriston and Brown. RCA Victor Recording, Brown Alumni Monthly v.56:8. May 1956
  - Commencement Address. Williams College, Williamstown, Massachusetts. June 10, 1956
  - Freedom and Responsibility. Volunteer Youth Leaders, Rockford, Illinois. September 12, 1956
  - New Range of Overseas Careers. Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse, New York. March 7, 1957
  - Survival and Freedom. Mike Wallace Interview. August 18, 1958
  - Point of View in International Affairs. Wesleyan University. December 10, 1958
  - How Beautiful America. Brown, Class of 1961. February 18, 1959
  - Seven Days. Junior Chapel, Brown. February 19, 1959
  - World Not to Get Out of Hand. Television: Providence Evening Bulletin, WJAR. February 24, 1959
  - Revolution of the American Citizen. United States Air Force Academy, Co. Assembly: International Stability and Progress. April 3, 1959
  - Thinking by Deputy. Vassar College Commencement. June 8, 1959
  - Awareness. Lafayette College, Easton, Pennsylvania. October 24, 1959
  - Student Responsibility. Junior-Senior Chapel. June 6, 1946
  - Function of Diplomacy. Advertising Council of America. November 20, 1959
  - Rugged Individualism. Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine. Annie Talbot Cole Lecture. March 22, 1960
  - How Can You Get Things Done in a Democracy. Great Challenge Series 1960, Symposium. April 3, 1960
  - Labels for People. Convocation, Brown. March 1, 1961
  - War and Peace. Brown Alumni, Hotel Roosevelt, New York. April 24, 1961
  - The United States and Tomorrow's World. United States Army War College, Carlisle, Pennsylvania. November 14, 1961
  - The United States and the United Nations. TC-CBC, Great Challenge Series 1961/62. February 1, 1962
- Reminiscences
  - Henry Merritt Wriston: Reminiscences of his career since 1907, May 1971 (Box 8)
    This document only includes the Wesleyan University section. It was assembled by Theodore R. Crane (Brown, class of 1950) with the assistance of Donald L. Salmon and Harold E. Van Horn.
- Interview
  - Conversation of Henry Merritt Wriston, Class of 1911, with Alphonsus J. Mitchell, Office of Public Relations, Wesleyan University, April 19, 1966
    Interview took place in Wriston's apartment, New York City. Lois E. Smith transcribed the tape recording. 2 copies.
- Addition of June 2008 (Acc. 2008-14)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume I (Box 9)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume IA (Box 9)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume II (Box 9)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume III (Box 9)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume IV (Box 9)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume V (Box 10)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume VI (Box 10)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume VII (Box 10)
  - Essays and Talks, 1916-1974, Volume VIII (Box 10)
  - Materials from the American Assembly (Box 11)
  - Materials from the Brown University Archives (Box 11)
    4 folders.
  - Materials from the Century Association Archives Foundation (Box 11)
  - Materials from Cassie Quintal (Box 11)
  - Materials from Kathy Wriston (Box 12)
    2 folders.
  - Materials from Wriston family (Box 12)
  - Other materials collected for website (Box 12)
  - List of Wriston speeches (Box 12)
  - Photographs from Cassy Quintal (Box 12)
    Includes disc.
  - Audio for website (Box 12)
    1 compact disc.
  - Audio: Wriston and Brown (Box 12)
  - Family audio (Box 12)
  - .wav files sent from Brown University (Box 12)